Register of the Georges de Serdici, baron, Papers, 1947-1990
Hoover Institution Archives
Georges de Serdici, baron, Papers,
1947-1990
91016
Serdici, Georges de, baron, 1920-
16 manuscript boxes 4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, press releases, depositions, legal documents, and printed matter, relating to political conditions in Romania; the trial of Iuliu Maniu, Vasile de Serdici and other leaders of the Partidul National Taranesc in 1947; Romanian émigré affairs; the Comitetul National Rom^an and other anti-communist organizations; and a lawsuit for defamation brought against Cicerone Ioanitoiu in France in 1985.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1991.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Political crimes and offenses -- Romania; Partidul National Taranesc; Maniu, Iuliu, 1873-1951; Serdici, Vasile de, baron, 1889-1953; Romanians in foreign countries; Anti-communist movements; Comitetul National Român; Ioanitoiu, Cicerone; Romania; Communism; Romania -- Politics and government, 1944-1989
Biography
1920 Born in Sarajevo, Yugoslavia. Son of Vasile de Serdici, former Romanian landowner and one of the leaders of the Romanian National Peasant Party (Partidul National Taranesc), one of the most important parties during the inter-war period
1947 Co-defense attorney in the trial organized by the Soviet NKVD and the Romanian communist secret services (Securitate) against the leadership of the Romanian National Peasant Party, including Iuliu Maniu and Vasile de Serdici
1948 March Escaped illegally from Romania. Since then, has been living in Sweden, Great Britain, and Germany, running his own businesses in real estate, oil, and shipping, and engaging relentlessly in anti-communist activities
1982-1990 Secretary General of the Romanian National Peasant Party, currently the majority party of the ruling coalition of Romania
1989 Won the lawsuit he brought against Cicerone Ioanitoiu in 1985
Scope and Content
Georges de Serdici's papers cover mainly the years he spent as an émigré in the U.S., after 1948. His writings and correspondence deal mostly with émigré affairs and with the lawsuit for defamation he brought against Cicerone Ioanitoiu in 1985.
The grounds for this lawsuit lie in the publication of Ioanitoiu's book entitled Tombes sans croix (Tombs without a cross). In this book related to the trial organized in 1947 by the NKVD and by the Romanian communist secret service, Securitate, against the elite democratic politicians, Ioanitoiu depicts Georges de Serdici's father (Vasile) as a "traitor." He accused Vasile de Serdici of delivering the archives of the National Peasant Party (PNT) to the communists, and of betraying the PNT's leader during the 1947 trial. Ioanitoiu also emphasized that this behavior was characteristic of Serdici, who left the army during war time in 1918 in order to serve as a witness to Prince Carol (future Carol II, King of Romania) in his wedding to Zizi Lambrino.
Bringing Alexandre Cretzianu, Emil Ghilizean, Cornel Bianu and others as witnesses, Georges de Serdici proved to the Court the irrelevance to the case of the second accusation, and the groundlessness of the first one. Like all political prisoners in Romania during the 1940s-1960s, his father was tortured both physically and psychologically, and administrated drugs, thus rendered many times irresponsible for his actions. That fact, corroborated by the proof that V. Serdici did not have in his possession any archival materials to deliver to the communists, enabled Georges de Serdici to win the case in 1989.
Also of special importance in the collection are the materials related to the Romanian section of Radio Free Europe, and its alleged collaboration with Securitate (see files 1-5 in box 6 and files 1 and 6-8 in box 7).
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1947-1983. (Box 1)
  Biographical notes, personal questionnaire, and resumes, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1948-1990. (Boxes 1-8.)
  Correspondence kept in original chronological files
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1948-1989. (Box 9)
  Articles, papers, radio broadcast transcripts, miscellaneous writings and notes, arranged chronologically by title
- SUBJECT FILE, 1952-1990. (Box 10)
  Communiqués, declarations, memoranda, regulations, speeches and writing by others, studies, clippings and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject
- "NATIONAL ACTION," 1951-1969. (Box 11)
  Correspondence, memoranda, and minutes of meetings, notes, protocols, and reports, arranged chronologically. The term "National Action" was used by Georges de Serdici to refer to the activity of Romanians in foreign countries (Europe and the U.S.)
- LAWSUIT AGAINST CICERONE IOANITOIU, 1982-1990. (Boxes 12-16)
  Correspondence with the lawyers, interpreters, and witnesses; clippings; excerpts from history books; legal reports; proceedings; translations; testimonies of witnesses; miscellaneous legal evidence, arranged chronologically
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1947-1983
  - Biographical notes, 1947-1983 (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Personal questionnaire for non-U.S. citizens of Radio Free Europe, 1957 (Folder 2)
  - Resumes, n.d. (Folder 3)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1948-1990.
  See also NATIONAL ACTION and LAWSUIT AGAINST CICERONE IOANITOIU
  - 1948. Includes correspondence with Alexandre Cretzianu, Alexandru Ghika, Grigore Niculescu Buzesti (Box 1., Folder 4)
  - 1949 (Folder 5)
  - 1950. Includes correspondence with Raoul Bossy (Folder 6)
  - 1951. Includes correspondence on Carol Davila; with International Federation of Free Journalists of Central and Eastern Europe and Baltic and Balkan Countries, and with National Committee for a Free Europe (Folder 7)
  - 1952.Includes correspondence with Dwight Eisenhower, Fundatia Regala Universitara "Carol I", Sabin Manuila, National Estonian Council, Constantin Visoianu (Folder 8-9)
  - 1953. Includes correspondence with Fundatia Regala Universitara "Carol I" (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - 1954. Includes correspondence with International Peasant Union (Folder 2)
  - 1955. Includes correspondence with Comitetul National Roman, Free Europe Committee, Radio Free Europe (Folder 3)
  - 1956. Includes correspondence with the Human Rights Division of the United Nations, International Peasant Union (Folder 4)
  - 1957. Includes correspondence with International Peasant Union (Folder 5)
  - 1959 (Folder 6)
  - 1963. Includes correspondence with Ion Ratiu (Folder 7)
  - 1964 (Folder 8)
  - 1965. Includes correspondence with Ion Ratiu (Folder 9)
  - 1966. Includes correspondence with Ion Ratiu (Folder 10)
  - 1967. Includes correspondence with Ion Ratiu (Folder 11)
  - 1968. Includes correspondence with Alexandre Ghika, Ion Ratiu (Folder 12)
  - 1969. Includes correspondence with Corneliu Coposu, Ion Ratiu (Folder 13)
  - 1970. Includes correspondence with Ion Ratiu (Folder 14)
  - 1971. Includes correspondence with Ion Ratiu (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - 1972. Includes correspondence with Michael, King of Romania, and Ion Ratiu (Folder 2)
  - 1973. Includes correspondence with Ion Ratiu (Folder 3)
  - 1974 (Folder 4)
  - 1975. Includes correspondence with Gerald Ford, Ion Ratiu (Folder 5-6)
  - 1976. Includes correspondence on Ion Ratiu (Folder 7)
  - 1977. Includes correspondence on Ion Ratiu (Folder 8)
  - 1978. Includes correspondence with Ion Ratiu (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - 1979. Includes correspondence with John Connaly, Ion Ratiu (Folder 2-3)
  - 1980 (Folder 4)
  - 1981 (Folder 5)
  - 1982Includes correspondence with Radu Campeanu; Michael, King of Romania; and with Radio Free Europe (Folder 6-7)
  - 1982. Includes correspondence with Michael, King of Romania (Box 5., Folder 1-2)
  - 1983. Includes correspondence with Radio Free Europe (Folder 3-6)
  - 1983. Includes correspondence on Vlad Georgescu, with Radio Free Europe, and Ion Ratiu (Box 6., Folder 1-2)
  - 1984. Includes correspondence with Max Campbelmann, Radio Free Europe, and on Vlad Georgescu (Folder 3-6)
  - 1984. Includes correspondence with Denis Diletant, Helmuth Kohl, and on Vlad Georgescu (Box 7., Folder 1-2)
  - 1985. Includes correspondence with Denis Diletant and with Ronald Reagan (Folder 3)
  - 1986 (Folder 4)
  - 1987. Includes correspondence with Ronald Reagan (Folder 5)
  - 1988. Includes correspondence with George Bush, John Whitehead, U.S. Department of State, and on Radio Free Europe (Folder 6-9)
  - 1988. Includes correspondence with Corneliu Coposu, Michail Gorbachev, Ronald Reagan (Box 8., Folder 1-3)
  - 1989. Includes correspondence with Charles, Prince of Wales; Mikhail Gorbachev; Michael, King of Romania; Michael Schapira; Leonid Zamiatin (Folder 4-8)
  - 1990. Includes correspondence with Corneliu Coposu (Folder 9)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1948-1989
  - "O Clarificare a domnului George Serdici," n.d. Typescript (Box 9., Folder 1)
  - "O Examinare a vestilor din tara," n.d. Typescript (Folder 2)
  - "Fuga din Romania," n.d. Typescript (Folder 3)
  - Notes on the Communist trial of the leaders of the Romanian National Party (PNT), n.d. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - "Primire romaneasca," n.d. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - "Report of the Regional Union of Free Journalists in Sweden," n.d. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - "Secretar General," n.d. Typescript (Folder 7)
  - Speech for the Estonian National Council, n.d. Typescript (Folder 8)
  - "Tragica drama a poporului roman," n.d. Typescript (Folder 9)
  - "La vie politique roumaine," n.d. Typescript (Folder 10)
  - "Rumansk Fascist Ryskt Trumfass Mot Maniu," Svenska Dagbladet, 1948 May 5. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - "Apell," 1952 June. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - "Ny Rod Giv I Rumanien," 1952 June 28. Typescript (Folder 13)
  - Comments printed in two Swedish newspapers regarding the alleged action against the Romanian legations in Stockholm and Copenhagen in 1955, 1955 February 16. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - "Cazul Lahovari," Dagens Nyheter, 1955 March 3. Typescript. Includes Romanian translation (Folder 15)
  - "Det Galler en Manniska," 1956 March 3. Typescript. Includes Romanian translation (Folder 16)
  - "Appeal," 1956 June. Typescript (Folder 17)
  - "La Rascruce de Drumuri," Vocea Libertatii, 1957 December 1. Typescript (Folder 18)
  - "German Minority in Romania," 1958 January. Typescript (Folder 19)
  - "Cinste lor," Vocea Libertatii, 1958 May. Typescript (Folder 20)
  - "Pina cind," 1963 May. Typescript (Folder 21)
  - "Punere la punct," 1963 June. Typescript (Folder 22)
  - "Citeva cuvinte in plus," 1963 July. Typescript (Folder 23)
  - "Ginduri pentru o noua indreptare a Actiunei Nationale," 1964 June-July. Typescript (Folder 24)
  - "Ziarul La Nation roumaine si fruntasii P.N.T.," 1964 September. Typescript (Folder 25)
  - "Framintarea exilului," 1964. Typescript (Folder 26)
  - "Declaratiile Domnului George Serdici," Vocea Libertatii, 1969. Typescript (Folder 27)
  - "President Nixon's Visit to Romania," 1969 July. Typescript (Folder 28)
  - "Romanian Greeting," International Herald Tribune, 1969 August 1. Typescript (Folder 29)
  - "Lifting the Vail of Confusion," B.I.R.E., 1969 September (Folder 30)
  - "Avertisment," 1971. Typescript (Folder 31)
  - "Criza Comitetul National Roman," 1975 February 20. Typescript (Folder 32)
  - "La Roumanie d'aujourd'hui a Dlui Ion Ratiu," 1975 June 10. Typescript (Folder 33)
  - "Conferinta Peneuropeana de Securitate de la Helsinki," 1975 June 23. Typescript (Folder 34)
  - "Importanta lui Rene Theo si a lui B.I.R.E.," 1977 November. Typescript (Folder 35)
  - "Comunicare din Partea Dlui George Serdici, Secretarul General al Partidului National Taranesc," 1982 November. Typescript. Includes English translation (Folder 36)
  - "6 Martie 1945," B.I.R.E., 1983 March (Folder 37)
  - "Punere la Punct," 1983 April 21. Typescript (Folder 38)
  - Statement relating to Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty, 1983 July 13. Typescript. Includes Romanian translation (Folder 39)
  - "Statement by Mr. George Serdici, Secretary General of the Romanian National Peasant Party, on the Recent Visit to Romania of Mr. George Bush, the Vice President of the United States," 1983 October. Typescript. Includes Romanian translation (Folder 40)
  - "Trading with Romania," Newsweek, 1983 December. Typescript (Folder 41)
  - "La Roumanie face au Kremlin," La Suisse, 1984 August 18 (Folder 42)
  - "Interview dat de catre domnul George Serdici doamnei Constatinescu si ziarului Curierul Romanesc dela Agered, Suedia," 1988 April 19. Typescript (Folder 43)
  - "Communicate," 1988 April. Typescript. Includes Romanian translation (Folder 44)
  - "Exilul Nostru Ar Putea Avea o Simnificatie," 1988 April-June (Folder 45)
  - "Vasile Serdici," 1988 June 28. Typescript (Folder 46)
  - "Romania: Communist Truths," 1989 September. Typescript (Folder 47)
  - "Communicato," 1989 May. Typescript (Folder 48)
  - "Note," 1989 July 9. Typescript (Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous notes. Holographs and typescripts (Folder 50)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1952-1990.
  Communiqués, declarations, memoranda, regulations, speeches and writings by others, studies, clippings and other printed matter
  - B.I.R.E. (Buletin de informatie pentru romanii din exil) (Box 10., Folder 1)
  - Campeanu, Radu (Folder 2)
  - Dialog (Folder 3)
  - Lambrino, Zizi (Folder 4)
  - National Peasant Party. Includes communiqués, copy of Iuliu Maniu's testament, regulations, and notes concerning the activity of the NPP's members in exile (Folder 5)
  - Pacepa, Ion (Folder 6)
  - Radio Free Europe (Folder 7)
  - Ratiu, Ion (Folder 8)
  - Romania - Politics and government (Folder 9)
    - 1944-1989
    - 1989- (Folder 10)
  - Romanian Nation (La Nation roumaine). Includes German translation (Folder 11)
  - Romanians in France (Folder 12)
  - Miscellany (Folder 13-15)
- "NATIONAL ACTION", 1951-1970.
  Includes correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes, protocols, and reports, relating to the activity of Romanians in foreign countries (Europe and the U.S.) and of the Comitetul National Roman
  - 1951-1952 (Box 11., Folder 1)
  - 1960-1963 (Folder 2)
  - 1964-1965 (Folder 3-7)
  - 1966-1970 (Folder 8-9)
- LAWSUIT AGAINST CICERONE IOANITOIU, 1982-1990.
  Correspondence with the lawyers, interpreters and witnesses; clippings; excerpts from history books; legal reports; proceedings; translations; testimonies of witnesses; miscellaneous legal evidence
  - 1982 (Box 12., Folder 1)
  - 1983 (Folder 2-4)
  - 1984 (Folder 5-8)
  - 1985 (Box 13., Folder 1-6)
  - 1985 (Box 14., Folder 1-6)
  - 1986 (Box 15., Folder 1-7)
  - 1987 (Box 16., Folder 1)
  - 1988 (Folder 2-3)
  - 1989 (Folder 4)
  - 1990 (Folder 5)